<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  The type III secretion system apparatus determines the intracellular niche of bacterial pathogens
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   Bacterial pathogens use a variety of strategies to evade host cell innate immune responses. For some, this includes the establishment of an intracellular replicative niche. Although many intracellular pathogens remodel phagosomes to support bacterial replication, others lyse their internalization vacuole to reside within the host cell cytosol. Little is currently known regarding how bacteria, particularly Gram-negative pathogens, mediate phagosomal escape. Using complementary reductionist and functional interchangeability experimental approaches, we demonstrate that the type III secretion system machinery itself directly modulates the extent to which bacteria escape from phagosomes. Given the high prevalence of type III secretion systems among intracellular bacterial pathogens, these studies have identified a potential means by which the intracellular niche of Gram-negative bacteria is defined.
  </p>
  <p>
   Upon entry into host cells, intracellular bacterial pathogens establish a variety of replicative niches. Although some remodel phagosomes, others rapidly escape into the cytosol of infected cells. Little is currently known regarding how professional intracytoplasmic pathogens, including
   <italic>
    Shigella
   </italic>
   , mediate phagosomal escape.
   <italic>
    Shigella,
   </italic>
   like many other Gram-negative bacterial pathogens, uses a type III secretion system to deliver multiple proteins, referred to as effectors, into host cells. Here, using an innovative reductionist-based approach, we demonstrate that the introduction of a functional
   <italic>
    Shigella
   </italic>
   type III secretion system, but none of its effectors, into a laboratory strain of
   <italic>
    Escherichia coli
   </italic>
   is sufficient to promote the efficient vacuole lysis and escape of the modified bacteria into the cytosol of epithelial cells. This establishes for the first time, to our knowledge, a direct physiologic role for the
   <italic>
    Shigella
   </italic>
   type III secretion apparatus (T3SA) in mediating phagosomal escape. Furthermore, although protein components of the T3SA share a moderate degree of structural and functional conservation across bacterial species, we show that vacuole lysis is not a common feature of T3SA, as an effectorless strain of
   <italic>
    Yersinia
   </italic>
   remains confined to phagosomes. Additionally, by exploiting the functional interchangeability of the translocator components of the T3SA of
   <italic>
    Shigella
   </italic>
   ,
   <italic>
    Salmonella
   </italic>
   , and
   <italic>
    Chromobacterium
   </italic>
   , we demonstrate that a single protein component of the T3SA translocon—
   <italic>
    Shigella
   </italic>
   IpaC,
   <italic>
    Salmonella
   </italic>
   SipC, or
   <italic>
    Chromobacterium
   </italic>
   CipC—determines the fate of intracellular pathogens within both epithelial cells and macrophages. Thus, these findings have identified a likely paradigm by which the replicative niche of many intracellular bacterial pathogens is established.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>