<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  SipA, SopA, SopB, SopD, and SopE2 Contribute to
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   The centisome 63 type III secretion system (T3SS-1) encoded by
   <italic>
    Salmonella
   </italic>
   pathogenicity island 1 (SPI1) mediates invasion of epithelial cells by
   <italic>
    Salmonella enterica
   </italic>
   serotype Typhimurium. Characterization of mutants lacking individual genes has revealed that T3SS-1 secreted proteins (effectors) SopE2 and SopB are required for invasion while the SipA protein accelerates entry into cells. Here we have revisited the question of which T3SS-1 effectors contribute to the invasion of epithelial cells by complementing a strain lacking all of the effector genes that are required to cause diarrhea in a calf (a
   <italic>
    sipA sopABDE2
   </italic>
   mutant). Introduction of either the cloned
   <italic>
    sipA
   </italic>
   , the cloned
   <italic>
    sopB
   </italic>
   , or the cloned
   <italic>
    sopE2
   </italic>
   gene increased the invasiveness of the
   <italic>
    sipA sopABDE2
   </italic>
   mutant for nonpolarized HT-29 cells. However, a contribution of
   <italic>
    sopA
   </italic>
   or
   <italic>
    sopD
   </italic>
   to invasion was not apparent when invasion assays were performed with the nonpolarized colon carcinoma cell lines T84 and HT-29. In contrast, introduction of either the
   <italic>
    sopA
   </italic>
   , the
   <italic>
    sopB
   </italic>
   , the
   <italic>
    sopD
   </italic>
   , or the
   <italic>
    sopE2
   </italic>
   gene increased the invasiveness of the
   <italic>
    sipA sopABDE2
   </italic>
   mutant for polarized T84 cells. Furthermore, introduction of a plasmid carrying
   <italic>
    sipA
   </italic>
   and
   <italic>
    sopB
   </italic>
   increased the invasiveness of the
   <italic>
    sipA sopABDE2
   </italic>
   mutant for polarized T84 cells significantly compared to the introduction of plasmids carrying only
   <italic>
    sipA
   </italic>
   or
   <italic>
    sopB
   </italic>
   . We conclude that SipA, SopA, SopB, SopD, and SopE2 contribute to
   <italic>
    S. enterica
   </italic>
   serotype Typhimurium invasion of epithelial cells in vitro.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>