<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Mycobacterium tuberculosis Serine/Threonine Protein Kinases
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p id="P1">
   The
   <italic>
    Mycobacterium tuberculosis
   </italic>
   genome encodes 11 serine/threonine protein kinases (STPKs). A similar number of two-component systems are also present, indicating that these two signal transduction mechanisms are both important in the adaptation of this bacterial pathogen to its environment. The
   <italic>
    M. tuberculosis
   </italic>
   phosphoproteome includes hundreds of Ser- and Thr-phosphorylated proteins that participate in all aspects of
   <italic>
    M. tuberculosis
   </italic>
   biology, supporting a critical role for the STPKs in regulating
   <italic>
    M. tuberculosis
   </italic>
   physiology. Nine of the STPKs are receptor type kinases, with an extracytoplasmic sensor domain and an intracellular kinase domain, indicating that these kinases transduce external signals. Two other STPKs are cytoplasmic and have regulatory domains that sense changes within the cell. Structural analysis of some of the STPKs has led to advances in our understanding of the mechanisms by which these STPKs are activated and regulated. Functional analysis has provided insights into the effects of phosphorylation on the activity of several proteins, but for most phosphoproteins the role of phosphorylation in regulating function is unknown. Major future challenges include characterizing the functional effects of phosphorylation for this large number of phosphoproteins, identifying the cognate STPKs for these phosphoproteins, and determining the signals that the STPKs sense. Ultimately, combining these STPK-regulated processes into larger, integrated regulatory networks will provide deeper insight into
   <italic>
    M. tuberculosis
   </italic>
   adaptive mechanisms that contribute to tuberculosis pathogenesis. Finally, the STPKs offer attractive targets for inhibitor development that may lead to new therapies for drug-susceptible and drug-resistant tuberculosis.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>