<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Role of host cell polarity and leading edge properties in
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   Type III secretion (T3S) functions in establishing infections in a large number of Gram-negative bacteria, yet little is known about how host cell properties might function in this process. We used the opportunistic pathogen
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas aeruginosa
   </italic>
   and the ability to alter host cell sensitivity to
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas
   </italic>
   T3S to explore this problem. HT-29 epithelial cells were used to study cellular changes associated with loss of T3S sensitivity, which could be induced by treatment with methyl-beta-cyclodextrin or perfringolysin O. HL-60 promyelocytic cells are innately resistant to
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas
   </italic>
   T3S and were used to study cellular changes occurring in response to induction of T3S sensitivity, which occurred following treatment with phorbol esters. Using both cell models, a positive correlation was observed between eukaryotic cell adherence to tissue culture wells and T3S sensitivity. In examining the type of adhesion process linked to T3S sensitivity in HT-29 cells, a hierarchical order of protein involvement was identified that paralleled the architecture of leading edge (LE) focal complexes. Conversely, in HL-60 cells, induction of T3S sensitivity coincided with the onset of LE properties and the development of actin-rich projections associated with polarized cell migration. When LE architecture was examined by immunofluorescent staining for actin, Rac1, IQ-motif-containing GTPase-activating protein 1 (IQGAP1) and phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase (PI3 kinase), intact LE structure was found to closely correlate with host cell sensitivity to
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   T3S. Our model for host cell involvement in
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas
   </italic>
   T3S proposes that cortical actin polymerization at the LE alters membrane properties to favour T3S translocon function and the establishment of infections, which is consistent with
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas
   </italic>
   infections targeting wounded epithelial barriers undergoing cell migration.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>