<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Th17-stimulating Protein Vaccines Confer Protection against
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   <italic>
    Rationale
   </italic>
   : New vaccine approaches are needed for
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas aeruginosa
   </italic>
   , which continues to be a major cause of serious pulmonary infections. Although Th17 cells can protect against gram-negative pathogens at mucosal surfaces, including the lung, the bacterial proteins recognized by Th17 cells are largely unknown and could be potential new vaccine candidates.
  </p>
  <p>
   <italic>
    Objectives
   </italic>
   : We describe a strategy to identify Th17-stimulating protein antigens of
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas aeruginosa
   </italic>
   to assess their efficacy as vaccines against pneumonia.
  </p>
  <p>
   <italic>
    Methods
   </italic>
   : Using a library of
   <italic>
    in vitro
   </italic>
   transcribed and translated
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   proteins, we screened for Th17-stimulating antigens by coculturing the library proteins with splenocytes from mice immunized with a live-attenuated
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   vaccine that is protective via Th17-based immunity. We measured antibody and Th17 responses after intranasal immunization of mice with the purified proteins mixed with the Th17 adjuvant curdlan, and we tested the protective efficacy of vaccination in a murine model of acute pneumonia.
  </p>
  <p>
   <italic>
    Measurements and Main Results
   </italic>
   : The proteins PopB, FpvA, FptA, OprL, and PilQ elicited strong IL-17 secretion in the screen, and purified versions of PopB, FpvA, and OprL stimulated high IL-17 production from immune splenocytes. Immunization with PopB, which is a highly conserved component of the type III secretion system and a known virulence factor, elicited Th17 responses and also enhanced clearance of
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   from the lung and spleen after challenge. PopB-immunized mice were protected from lethal pneumonia in an antibody-independent, IL-17–dependent manner.
  </p>
  <p>
   <italic>
    Conclusions
   </italic>
   : Screening for Th17-stimulating protein antigens identified PopB as a novel and promising vaccine candidate for
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   .
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>