<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Translocon-Independent Intracellular Replication by
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p id="P2">
   <italic>
    Pseudomonas aeruginosa,
   </italic>
   a significant cause of human morbidity and mortality, uses a type 3 secretion system (T3SS) to inject effector toxins into host cells. We previously reported that
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   uses ADP-ribosyltransferase (ADPr) activity of the T3SS effector ExoS for intracellular replication. T3SS translocon (Δ
   <italic>
    popB
   </italic>
   )-mutants, which can export, but not translocate effectors across host membranes, retained intracellular replication. We hypothesized that secreted effectors mediate translocon-independent intracellular replication. Translocon mutants of PAO1 lacking one or more of its three known effectors (ExoS, ExoT and ExoY) were used. All translocon mutants, irrespective of effectors expressed, localized to intracellular vacuoles. Translocon-effector null mutants and translocon-
   <italic>
    exoS
   </italic>
   mutants showed defective intracellular replication. Mutants in
   <italic>
    exoT
   </italic>
   ,
   <italic>
    exoY
   </italic>
   or both replicated as efficiently as translocon mutants expressing all effectors. Complementation of translocon-effector null mutants with native
   <italic>
    exoS
   </italic>
   or a membrane localization domain mutant of
   <italic>
    exoS
   </italic>
   , but not the ADPr mutant
   <italic>
    exoS
   </italic>
   (pUCP
   <italic>
    exoS
   </italic>
   E381D), restored intracellular replication, correlating with increased bacteria per vacuole. Thus,
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   is capable of intravacuolar replication that requires ExoS ADPr activity, but not the translocon. These data suggest that T3SS effectors can participate in pathogenesis without translocon-mediated translocation across host membranes, and that intracellular bacteria can contribute to
   <italic>
    P. aeruginosa
   </italic>
   pathogenesis within epithelial cells.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>