<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article>
 <title>
  Flagellar Motility Is a Key Determinant of the Magnitude of the Inflammasome Response to
 </title>
 <abstract>
  <p>
   We previously demonstrated that bacterial flagellar motility is a fundamental mechanism by which host phagocytes bind and ingest bacteria. Correspondingly, loss of bacterial motility, consistently observed in clinical isolates from chronic
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    Pseudomonas aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   infections, enables bacteria to evade association and ingestion of
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   by phagocytes both
   <italic>
    in vitro
   </italic>
   and
   <italic>
    in vivo
   </italic>
   . Since bacterial interactions with the phagocyte cell surface are required for type three secretion system-dependent NLRC4 inflammasome activation by
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   , we hypothesized that reduced bacterial association with phagocytes due to loss of bacterial motility, independent of flagellar expression, will lead to reduced inflammasome activation. Here we report that inflammasome activation is reduced in response to nonmotile
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   . Nonmotile
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   elicits reduced IL-1β production as well as caspase-1 activation by peritoneal macrophages and bone marrow-derived dendritic cells
   <italic>
    in vitro
   </italic>
   . Importantly, nonmotile
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   also elicits reduced IL-1β levels
   <italic>
    in vivo
   </italic>
   in comparison to those elicited by wild-type
   <named-content content-type="genus-species">
    P. aeruginosa
   </named-content>
   . This is the first demonstration that loss of bacterial motility results in reduced inflammasome activation and antibacterial IL-1β host response. These results provide a critical insight into how the innate immune system responds to bacterial motility and, correspondingly, how pathogens have evolved mechanisms to evade the innate immune system.
  </p>
 </abstract>
 <sentences/>
</article>